Pose one of the twelve Yoga poses in Shivananda Yoga is Headstand, Sirsasana.
And, I'm going to have Jim here demonstrating the Headstand.
Ok. First and most important thing about Headstand is you start and you end in Child Pose. The last thing you want to do is kind of throw the blood up to the brain and then just kind of throw it back out.
So, I'm going to have him come into Child Pose first.
Relax, take two nice deep breaths.
Find that nice calming center.
The most important part about Headstand is your base, your tripod.
So I'm going to have him go ahead and push up to the elbows measuring off.
Very important.
As long as you practice Headstand, always measure off.
You want to get a good distance there.
Now, bringing the hands forward.
Hold on, hold on.
Coming forward.
Now, without moving the elbows you bring the arms forward.
Make sure you don't let them come out and apart.
Because this is your base for your Headstand.
Alright.
Now placing your spot on your head where you would balance a book onto the floor.
Now, notice his fingers aren't clinched.
They're nicely relaxed and the thumbs are kind of braced on the back of the head.
Now go ahead and tuck your toes.
Straighten the legs out.
Slowly walk a little bit forward until you have a nice long spine.
And just lift.
See how he just lifts up the knees?
Try not to ever kick up into Headstand.
Then, slowly lifting up.
Beautiful.
Now if he is going to be pressing equally into his tripod pulling in through the belly giving yourself a nice base.
Keep pressing into your tripod.
Keeping pulling in through your belly.
And you get a beautiful Headstand.
Headstand is a very healthy pose to do for yourself.
It relieves the cardiovascular system.
Think about all that little blood that takes longer to get to the heart.
This way it's just slowly flowing down gently.